[
{
  "question": "Calculate the change in entropy per kilogram as air is heated from 300 to 600 K while pressure drops from 400 to 300 kPa.",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      T1 = 300 # Initial Temperature (K)\n     T2 = 600 # Final Temperature (K)\n     P1 = 400 # Initial Pressure (kPa)\n     P2 = 300 # Final Pressure (kPa)\n     Cp = 1.005 # Specific heat capacity at constant pressure (kJ/kg-K)\n     R = 0.287 # Specific Gas constant (kJ/kg-K)\n\n      # Using equation for Entropy changes for perfect gases, ds = s2 - s1\n     ds = Cp*np.log(T2/T1) - R*np.log(P2/P1)\n\n     print('The change in specific entropy of air is: ', ds, 'kJ/kg-K')\n      ",
  "explanation": "This code calculates the change in specific entropy as the temperature and pressure of air are varied. It employs the perfect gas relations with the equation for entropy change",
	"reference": "Fundamentals of Thermodynamics, 8th Edition, by Borgnakke and Sonntag, page 275."
},
{
  "question": "A cylinder fitted with a piston has an initial volume of 0.1 m3 and contains nitrogen at 150 kPa, 25 C. The piston is moved, compressing the nitrogen until the pressure is 1 MPa and the temperature is 150 C. During this compression process heat is transferred from the nitrogen, and the work done on the nitrogen is 20 kJ. Determine the amount of this heat transfer",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      V = 0.1 # Initial volume (m^3)\n     P1 = 150 # Inital pressure (kPa)\n     P2 = 1 # Final pressure (MPa)\n     T1 = 25 # Initial temperature (C)\n     T2 = 150 # Final temperature (C)\n     W = -20 # Work done (kJ)\n     R = 0.2968 # Specfic gas constant for Nitrogen (kJ/kg-K)\n     Cv = 0.745 # Specific heat constant at constant volume for Nitrogen (kJ/kg-K)\n\n     # Using ideal gas relations, pV = mRT, can find mass of nitrogen\n     m = (P1*V)/(R*(T1+273.15))\n\n     # From the equations for first law and internal energy, dQ -dW = dU, du = Cv * dT\n     Q = m *Cv*(T2-T1) + W\n\n     print('The heat transfer due to compression from the nitrogen is: ', Q, 'kJ')\n      ",
  "explanation": "Here, the code calculates the amount of heat transfer done during the compression process of a piston. It uses the ideal gas relation, pV = mRT, and the first law of thermodynamics Q - W = U, where U is the internal energy.",
	"reference": "Fundamentals of Thermodynamics, 8th Edition, by Borgnakke and Sonntag, page 119."
},
{
  "question": "A flow of air has velocity of 850 m/s, pressure of 130 kPa, and temperature at 180 C. Compute the pressure and temperature of the air if brought isentropically to rest.",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Cp = 1005 # Specific heat capacity of air at constant pressure (J/kg-K)\n     gamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\n     V1 = 850 # Inital velocity of air (m/s)\n     P1 = 130 # Initial pressure of air (kPa)\n     T1 = 180 # Initial temperature of air (C)\n\n     # Stagnation temperature due to steady isentropic process\n     T2 = (T1 + 273.15) + (V1**2)/(2*Cp)\n\n     # Stagnation pressure using isentropic relations\n     P2 = P1*(T2/(T1 + 273.15))**((gamma)/(gamma - 1))\n\n     print ('The stagnation temperature and pressure of air due to isentropic process is ', T2, 'K, ',P2, 'kPa, respectively' )\n      ",
  "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation temperature and pressure which is if it were brought to zero velocity by steady isentropic process with no external work. With these assumptions, we use the equation for stagnation temperature, T01 = T1 + v1^2/2Cp. And to find stagnation pressure, we use the isentropic relations between pressure and temperature, p0/p1 = (T0/T1)^(k/k-1), where k is the specific heat ratio, gamma.",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "A chemical is flowing through a pipe with 90Â° bend, with a mass flow of 200 kg/s. Its incoming velocity (uniform) is 2 m/s, and its outgoing velocity is 3 m/s. What is the net force exerting on the fluid and its magnitude?",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     mdot = 200 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\n     V1 = 2 # Incoming velocity (m/s)\n     V2 = 3 # Outgoing velocity (m/s)\n\n     # Momentum flux and conservation of mass, find force compenents\n     Fx = mdot * (0 - V1)\n     Fy = mdot * (V2 - 0)\n     Fz = 0\n     Fnet = [Fx, Fy, Fz]\n\n     # Magnitude of net force\n     Fmag = np.sqrt(Fx**2 + Fy**2 + Fz**2)\n\n     Force = ['Fx', 'Fy', 'Fz']\n\n      print ('The net force exerting on the fluid is:', Force, '= ', Fnet, 'N and the magnitude is:',Fmag ,'N' )\n      ",
  "explanation": "This code calculates the net force exerting on the fluid around a bend. Assuming incoming velocity is in the positive x direction and outgoing velocity is in the positive y direction, we can find individual components of force using the momentum flux equation (Fx = mDotOut * vOut - mDotIn * vIn) and idea of concervation of mass (mDotOut = mDotIn). We can assume flow is inviscid.",
	"reference": "Jack B. Evett, Cheng Liu, 2500 Solved Problems in Fluid mechanics and Hydraulics, Revised First Edition."
},
{
  "question": "A needle nose projectile traveling at a speed of M = 3 passes 200m above an observer. Find the projectiles velocity and determine how far beyond the observer the projectile will first be heard.",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     M = 3 # Mach number of projectile\n     h = 200 # Height of projectile (m)\n     k = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio (gamma)\n     R = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/kg-K)\n\n     # Assuming the temperature of air is room temperature\n     T = 300 # (K)\n\n     # Speed of sound (m/s)\n     a = np.sqrt(k*R*T)\n\n     # Velocity of projectile (m/s)\n     V = M*a\n\n     # Wave angle calculation (rad)\n     u = np.arcsin(1/M)\n\n     # Distance of sound heard beyond observer\n     x = (h)/(np.tan(u))\n\n     print('The velocity of the projectile is: ',V, 'm/s')\n     print('The distance beyond the observer which projectile is first heard is: ', x, 'm')\n      ",
  "explanation": "This code involves a projectile moving at supersonic speed which creates a mach wave. Knowing the air conditions, the speed of sound can be calculated using a = sqrt(kRT). Thus, the velocity of the projectile can be found. Given the observer is stationary, the wave angle can be calculated using u = sin-1(1/M) and with trigonometry, the distance of the heard projectile is found using tan(u) = h/x.",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Water enters a stationary lawn sprinkler through its base at the steady rate of 1000 ml/s. The exit area of each of the two nozzles is 30 mm^2. Determine the average speed of water leaving the nozzle.",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Q = 0.001 # Volumetric flow rate (m^3/s) = 1000/10^6\n     A = 30/(10**6) # Area of nozzles (m^2)\n\n     # Conservation of mass (Continuity), A2*v2 + A3*v3 - A1*v1 = 0\n     # A2 = A3 and v2 = v3. Therefore, average velocity of water exiting the nozzle is\n     velNozzle = Q/(2*A)\n\n     print ('The velocity of water leaving the nozzle is: ',velNozzle, 'm/s')\n      ",
  "explanation": "First, assume that flow is steady and incompressible. Then, by continuity the mass flow rate entering the sprinkler and exiting sprinkler is equal, A2*v2 + A3*v3 - A1*v1 = 0, density cancels out as it is constant throughout. Knowing the volumetric flow rate entering equal to Q = A1*v1 and that the areas of the nozzles are equal, we arrive at the equation above.",
	"reference": "Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics, Sixth edition, Bruce R. Munson, Donald F. Young, page 197."
},
{
  "question": "Suppose you have two blocks of copper, each of heat capacity 200 J/K. Initially one block has a uniform temperature of 300 K and the other 310 K. Calculate the entropy change that occurs when you place the two blocks in thermal contact with one another and surround them with perfect thermal insulation. Is the sign of delta S consistent with the second law? (Assume the process occurs at constant volume.",
  "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Cv = 200 # Heat capacity at constant volume (J/K)\n     Tc = 300 # Temperature of the cooler block (K)\n     Th = 310 # Temperature of the warmer block (K)\n\n     # Final equiliubrium temperature of blocks\n     Teq = (Tc + Th)/2\n\n     # Entropy changes of individual blocks\n     Sc = Cv * np.log(Teq/Tc)\n     Sh = Cv * np.log(Teq/Th)\n\n     # Total entropy change\n     Stot = Sc + Sh\n\n     print('The entropy change of the cooler and warmer block are: ',Sc, 'J/K and', Sh, 'J/K, respectively.')\n     print('The total entropy change is: ',Stot, 'J/k which is positive as predicted by the second law for irreversible process in isolated systems.')\n      ",
  "explanation": "Since the blocks have equal heat capacities, a given quantity of heat transfer from the warmer to the cooler block causes temperature changes that are equal in magnitude and of opposite signs. The final equilibrium temperature is 305 K, the average of the initial values. When the temperature of one of the blocks changes reversibly from T1 to T2 , the entropy change is given by dS = integral(Cv*dT/T) from T1 to T2 == Cv*ln(T2/T1). The infinitesimal entropy production due to irreverisibility cannot be negative.",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Discuss the implications of entropy generation in irreversible processes and its relationship to the second law of thermodynamics.",
  "answer": "Entropy represents the thermal energy's inability to perform useful work. In irreversible processes, entropy generation occurs due to dissipative phenomena like turbulence and friction, moving systems towards thermodynamic equilibrium, where entropy is maximized. The second law of thermodynamics asserts that in an isolated system, entropy always increases for irreversible processes and remains constant for reversible ones. The Clausius inequality further states that entropy production due to irreversibility is always positive.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Discuss the concept of shock waves and expansion fans and their impact on flow properties.",
  "answer": "Shock waves are caused when flow velocity exceeds the speed of sound and/or there is an abrupt decrease in flow area. Across a shock, static pressure, temperature, and density increase almost instantaneously and the mach number decreases. Expansion fans occur when flow passes a convex corner and the changes in flow properties are opposite of shocks. Because flow accross shocks is non-isentropic, total pressure downstream of the shock is less than upstream. As expansions fans are isentropic, the total pressure remains constant.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Explain how Bernoulli's equation applies to parallel and curved streamlines. How does pressure vary in bends? Under what conditions is it valid?",
  "answer": "For this, neglect the effects of gravity. In parallel streamlines, dp/dr = 0, meaning there is no pressure gradient and the equation is simply P + 1/2*rho*v^2 = const. In curved streamlines of radius r, dp/dr = rho*(v^2/r) where v is the tangential velocity, there is a pressure gradient across the streamlines. Therefore, having this additional term, outside a bend as the radius is larger, the pressure is larger. Bernoulli's equation is only valid for flows that are steady, incompressible, and inviscid (no flow friction).",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "What is the difference between a system and a control volume, why is it important?",
  "answer": "A system is a region of space in which the mass remains constant, meaning mass cannot cross the system boundary. It can also alter its shape and volume. In control volumes mass is allowed to cross its boundaries but cannot alter its shape of volume. However, it can move at constant speed. A system can be applied to a piston containing gas under compression and expansion to find the work done and heat transferred. And in fluid flow, control volumes are easier to apply when mass is flowing into and out of a control volume. ",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Explain static, dynamic, stagnation pressure and how they relate in a pitot-static probe?",
  "answer": "Static pressure,p, is the actual pressure at any given point in the flow. It is the pressure measured using a tube placed perpendicular to the flow. Stagnation temperature, p0, is the maximum pressure a fluid can reach when brought to rest isentropically with mechanical losses, i.e., p0 = p + 1/2 * density * velocity^2. It is measured by a pitot-tube facing directly towards the flow at which the fluid velocity is zero at the tube opening. Dynamic pressure is found by taking the stagnation pressure minus the static pressure. Pitot-static probes are placed on aircraft to calculate its speed using Bernoulli's equation.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "Consider a cyclic heat engine operating between two heat reservoirs at different temperatures. Explain how the efficiency of the engine changes if the temperature of the cold reservoir is increased while keeping the temperature of the hot reservoir constant.",
  "answer": "First, given the parameters, assume the process is reversible. The efficiency of a heat engine is given by the ratio of the work output to the heat input. For reversible processes, we can write the efficiency,n, as n = 1 - Tc/Th, where Tc and Th are temperatures of the cold and hot reservoir respectively. As the temperature of the cold reservoir (Tc) is increased while keeping the temperature of the hot reservoir (Th) constant, the efficiency of the engine decreases. This is because the temperature difference (Th - Tc) decreases. ",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "How is choked flow achieved in a convergent nozzle and what are its implications?",	
  "answer": "The fluid velocity can be manipulated by changing the exit static pressure. Choked flow occurs when the fluid reaches Mach 1 at the throat. To achieve Mach 1, the exit static pressure is decreased until the ratio of inlet stagnation pressure over exit static pressure reaches around 1.893. Once you hit Mach 1, flow velocity cannot increase further, even if the exit static pressure decreases. Therefore, the mass flow rate cannot increase and reaches its maximum.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "How and why does an increase in the skin friction coefficient affect flow conditions in Fanno flow?",
  "answer": "The increase in friction represents greater wall shear stress as given by the equation Cf = t/(1/2*rho*v^2) where t is the wall shear stress. As t increases, the pressure drop along a duct increases due to larger pressure losses given by dp/dx = -4t/D. As friction serves to reduce the effective area, the choked flow conditions will be reached at a shorter duct length.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
},
{
  "question": "On a T-s diagram, compare the constant pressure and volume lines. How are isentropic processes related?",
  "answer": "For constant pressure, dp = 0, therefore the Tds equation simplifies to (dT/ds) = T/Cp, showing that the constant pressure line has a positive slope. As temperature increases, the slope increases. For constant volume, the Tds equation is (dT/ds) = T/Cv. Since, Cv < Cp for a perfect gas, the constant volume line is steeper. An isentropic compression process is represented as a vertical line from a lower constant pressure line to a higher one. The opposite is true for an isentropic expansion process.",
  "explanation":"",
  "reference":""
}
]